<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<elements>
  <info>
    <name>Shinigami</name>
    <description>Spiritual warriors who maintain the balance between life and death.</description>
    <author url="https://github.com/cyanidehigh/Cynful-Aurora">Cynful Aurora Project</author>
    <update version="1.0">
      <file name="races/race-shinigami.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/cyanidehigh/Cynful-Aurora/main/races/race-shinigami.xml"/>
    </update>
  </info>
  
  <element name="Shinigami" type="Race" source="Bleach DND 5E" id="ID_RACE_SHINIGAMI">
    <description>
      <p class="flavor">Shinigami, or Soul Reapers, are spiritual beings who preserve the balance between the living world and the afterlife. They wield Zanpakutō—manifestations of their souls—to guide spirits and combat Hollows.</p>
      
      <h4>SPIRITUAL ESSENCE</h4>
      
      <p>Each Shinigami possesses unique spiritual energy, known as Reiatsu. This energy fuels their abilities and grants them awareness of the unseen world.</p>
      
      <h4>SHINIGAMI TRAITS</h4>
      
      <p>
        <span class="feature">Ability Score Increase.</span>Your Wisdom score increases by 2, and your Dexterity score increases by 1.<br/>
        <span class="feature">Age.</span>Shinigami mature at the same rate as humans but can live for centuries due to their spiritual nature.<br/>
        <span class="feature">Alignment.</span>Most Shinigami tend toward lawful alignments, valuing duty and structure.<br/>
        <span class="feature">Size.</span>Shinigami are similar in build to humans. Your size is Medium.<br/>
        <span class="feature">Speed.</span>Your base walking speed is 30 feet.<br/>
        <span class="feature">Languages.</span>You can speak, read, and write Common and Spiritual Tongue.<br/>
      </p>
      
      <h4>RACIAL FEATURES</h4>
      
      <p>
        <span class="feature">Spiritual Awareness.</span>You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks to detect ethereal or undead creatures.<br/>
        <span class="feature">Reiatsu Control.</span>Once per long rest, as a bonus action, you can empower your attacks with spiritual energy. For 1 minute, you add your proficiency bonus to attack and damage rolls.<br/>
        <span class="feature">Soul Form.</span>As an action, you can separate from your physical body (if applicable), entering a spirit state for up to 10 minutes. You can pass through non-magical barriers and see into the Ethereal Plane, but you cannot interact with solid matter. Once per long rest.<br/>
        <span class="feature">Zanpakutō Affinity.</span>You gain proficiency with longswords, treating one as your Zanpakutō. You may use Wisdom instead of Strength or Dexterity for attack and damage rolls when wielding it.<br/>
      </p>
    </description>
    
    <sheet display="false"/>
      <setters>
        <set name="height" modifier="2d8">5'4"</set>
        <set name="weight" modifier="2d4">130 lb.</set>
      </setters>
      
      <rules>
        <stat name="wisdom" value="2"/>
        <stat name="dexterity" value="1" />
        <stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base"/>
        <grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM"/>
        <grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_COMMON"/>
        <grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_SPIRITUAL_TONGUE"/>
        <grant type="Proficiency" id="ID_PROFICIENCY_WEAPON_LONGSWORD"/>
        <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SPIRITUAL_AWARENESS"/>
        <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_REIATSU_CONTROL"/>
        <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SOUL_FORM"/>
        <grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ZANPAKUTO_AFFINITY"/>
      </rules>
  </element>
  
  <element name="Spiritual Awareness" type="Racial Trait" source="Bleach DND 5E" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SPIRITUAL_AWARENESS">
    <description>
      <p>You can perceive spirits and invisible entities. You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks to detect ethereal or undead creatures.</p>
    </description>
    
    <sheet>
      <description>Advantage on Perception checks to detect ethereal or undead entities.</description>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  
  <element name="Reiatsu Control" type="Racial Trait" source="Bleach DND 5E" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_REIATSU_CONTROL">
    <description>
      <p>Once per long rest, you can channel your spiritual energy to empower your strikes. For 1 minute, add your proficiency bonus to attack and damage rolls.</p>
    </description>
    
    <sheet>
      <description>Once per long rest, add proficiency bonus to attack and damage rolls for 1 minute.</description>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  
  <element name="Soul Form" type="Racial Trait" source="Bleach DND 5E" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_SOUL_FORM">
    <description>
      <p>As an action, you can separate from your body and become a spirit for 10 minutes. You can pass through non-magical barriers and see into the Ethereal Plane, but cannot interact with solid matter. Once per long rest.</p>
    </description>
    
    <sheet>
      <description>Once per long rest, enter spirit form for 10 minutes; pass through barriers, see the Ethereal Plane.</description>
    </sheet>
  </element>
  
  <element name="Zanpakutō Affinity" type="Racial Trait" source="Bleach DND 5E" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ZANPAKUTO_AFFINITY">
    <description>
      <p>You are proficient with longswords, your Zanpakutō. You may use Wisdom instead of Strength or Dexterity for attack and damage rolls when wielding it.</p>
    </description>
    
    <sheet>
      <description>Use Wisdom for longsword attack and damage rolls; counts as Zanpakutō.</description>
    </sheet>
  </element>

</elements>
